[Music]
okay I mean that's not at all what it's
about by the way uh oiro another round
of applause for
[Applause]
oiro the reason I have him up here is so
he I'm not going to look at him he can
secretly get of you guys a thumbs up and
thumbs down if I'm talking [__] and
making lies up here okay cuz that's the
whole point so um I'm going to try and
make this quick I'm not that great of a
public speaker but if you hopefully we
get to the questions quick and start
thinking of them now
um so it's called you don't oh I should
introduce myself again Nigel Lowry I
work at devolver digital uh so you don't
need a [__] publisher um but if you
do ask questions and that's what this
really is about it was a little
misleading of a title um I think that
one of the biggest things that people
need to know is that uh you don't need a
publisher I think everyone knows that by
now and this is what this discussion is
about that if you do start asking
questions um mostly like I said it's
going to be about asking questions not
right now no one go to the mic
but um the fundamental part of getting
any sort of business deal at all uh
including getting a publisher is to uh
kind of ask questions know everything
you can possibly oh people are still
coming in
welcome oh wait I'm just kidding um this
might be a short presentation actually
I'll end up being long because I I'll
Mumble a lot but I invite you to start
thinking of these questions now because
I think I'm here I want to answer them
um this is a form in which I can kind of
give you some information but I do want
you guys to think of questions cuz I'm
I'm happy to uh answer as many as I can
and I'll stay late I don't I have
nothing else to do I'm a really I'm a
really sad person uh so a few
disclosures uh the first being I also
you know I work at an indie publisher
like I mentioned before and the reason I
wanted to do this talk is we get a lot
of pictures literally dozens and dozens
of [__]
[__] please do not tell my wife I
said
that and it's become very clear that a
lot of developers don't really know
either to even ask questions or the
right questions to ask and who to ask
them to uh like in the industry gaming
is fantastic but there's good guys
there's bad guys and there's good guys
that don't what the [__] they're doing
and and maybe you know aren't providing
all the information that they should so
maybe I can make some decent points
today talk about what we're uh what we
look for what to look for excuse me and
what to ask about before signing an
agreement so this is the agenda AKA last
chance leave before it's rude um with
that said you know um this is not going
to have a lot of charts and data this is
almost all entirely anecdotal stuff my
intention here is to pass on information
to everybody here from my side of the
fence from the evil publish publisher
side of the fence and bring to light
some of the issues and challenges that
crop up even in our business and things
I hear from developers I talk
to so Indie Publishers one board in
every minute right oh I'm going to back
up the things I'm going to talk about
actually are Indie Publishers what is
that what the [__] does that even mean
um publisher partner are those things uh
you know the same thing are they
different I think that's kind of the
Crux of this conversation and then uh
common issues common issues we just kind
of
see so any Publishers AKA one born one
born every minute um when I was thinking
about what I was going to say here I
kept coming back to this inherent
struggle uh that small developers have
on why they might even look for a
publisher uh the game Market is
wonderful amazing but you know you're
all pouring your heart and soul into
these in these games and it can become
pretty terrifying when it's time to
either really work on it or it's getting
and you want to launch right so often
times developers don't want to go it
alone and this kind of made me think of
this famous scene from the opening
moments Legend of Zelda where link is
about to embark on this Grand Adventure
right and uh he walks into this room and
some old dude tosses him a sword and
gives him a warning right link takes it
and doesn't ask a single question just
rolls out assumes because this guy knows
what he's done he been there knows what
he's doing is going to give him all the
information he needs um what do we find
out yes the sword was helpful but it was
not the only tool that actually needed
he needed quite a few things to finish
his his Adventure um and uh there was
more things necessary to complete this
task than just this sword so he didn't
ask questions he doesn't know who this
guy is or what he did um and he doesn't
know what kind of cut this guy has taken
off the back end of this adventure right
maybe maybe this guy's getting 75% of
all the rupes that he collects we don't
even know and what happened to link he
didn't ask questions and he ended up in
a shitty sequel I'm saying it all the
two
sucks so so Publishers have been around
for nearly as long as game developers
but I did zero research on the subject
so that might not be true but what I'm
certain is there's always been this
animosity between uh developers and
Publishers and you know rightfully so um
the latest I think most obvious thing is
at the end of every Kickstarter people
mention you know why are they doing this
Kickstarter well CU you know they want
to avoid Publishers because they're bad
they they'll ruin creativity they'll
take a hold of the game they're going to
cheat them out of money and honestly you
know public have behaved badly for years
and this is a an absolutely perfect like
rational thing to say um but this
happens all the time and it's
unfortunate and there's some good people
out there and there's some bad people
like I said before but this happens all
the time but I do think the game has
changed I think everyone in this room
this is not news the game has changed uh
digital distribution I put the little
exclamation marks cuz I'm not as good as
ajiro at Graphics but I put these sweet
exclamation par marks up there because
digital distribution is a point that
really changed a lot of things it uh
bestowed an unbelievable amount of
Leverage with the developer that changed
everything because you can get directly
to your
consumers um this is an important moment
and for now like I said has shifted this
kind of perceived
power so we've seen those bar graphs
those charts where uh there's huge
acceleration in the number of games
being released on Steam the App Store
everything like that and you can argue a
lot of different reasons digital
distribution is one um accessible tools
less stringent curation on these
storefronts but that's not the news
everyone knows there's a lot of games
out here I especially think this
audience knows there's a shitload of
games out there right but what's
interesting to us is hey Evan I just saw
you sorry um what's news to us is that
or not what's interesting to us is there
a lot of service providers now people uh
whether it's a publisher or a
localization company there's a lot of
things being built up around indie games
and any game developers uh a service
provider like I said can be anyone from
a localization company to a testing
Studio but there's more and more of
these right and game Publishers are no
exception the Indie publisher Market has
lots of options now okay uh devolver
being one and in the middle but as you
can see this is a small example of of of
the different Publishers you can go with
um what's important is to understand
each one's Direction their strategy
their
capabilities and uh know what's right
for your game the names up on this
screen these two screens I didn't know
there was going to be two screens the
names up on these two screens are just a
handful of companies to consider um
they're Publishers they're game labels
they're whatever but they're all have
their own kind of thing of taking your
game working with your game and getting
it to a large audience uh Sony Computer
Entertainment obviously has their kind
of angle to do it Indie fund specialized
in obviously funding Indies and having
really really friendly uh uh developer
agreements and folks like Team 17 Adult
Swim and double fine are fantastic
groups that can release your game but
they're developers themselves and they
can offer a lot of uh Insight in the
game development my point here is a
publisher can mean a lot of different
things so I'm going to lump them all
together but they all have you know
their own minutia and details of what
they might specialize
in water
sorry okay so I want to get to the meat
of this we know that there's a shitload
of options I'm cussing a lot I'm
apologize there's a ton of options out
there uh when a developer wants to find
a publisher to work with and now you
need to get to this vetting process
right what's going to work for you
what's going to work for your team and
what's going to work for uh the game
itself s so most of the developers that
we talk to the discussion starts around
what is what is the publisher going to
do for me and then it kind of works its
way towards what can you do for my game
and that's kind of an important kind of
evolution of that discussion so the best
way I thought when I was thinking about
what to say here is to frame this uh by
categorizing categorizing this into what
are things that a publisher should do
for you and what are things that a
partner should do for you now these
things aren't necessarily at odds with
each other but they don't also
necessarily always come hand inand so
this is what I want people be careful to
when they're talking to Publishers
Partners game labels whatever it's being
called These Days um you need to find
out um the potential publisher you're
working for and find out what they're
going to do for you and what that you
are looking for in a partner and
reconcile those two things okay because
that's what's really really important
you don't want to uh pay for things
basically that you're not going to use
and you want to find uh a publisher can
do all the things you needed to
do okay so what can a publisher provide
um these are the basic things that
people think about when they're talking
about a publisher um a developer can
hypothetically do all of these things
themselves actually not hypothetically
they can do all these things themselves
and that's why it's called
self-publishing and a lot of people do
it the reason people like ojiro uh work
with us is because they don't want to do
them and they think that a publisher can
do them better and more efficiently
right so they can focus on making the
game give the thumbs up right now
okay your royalty check is it's due
uh so these are the base level things
though okay these are these aren't
things that should excite you these are
what you should be expecting from a
publisher um I don't really want to
dwell on all of them um and I'm not
going to go in too much detail but I do
want to talk about marketing
distribution is I think these are the
areas that are maybe most foreign to
developers and uh maybe distinguishing
characteristics I guess between
different Publishers you can talk to so
marketing um marketing is like saying
I'm a game develop it's game development
like what does that mean there's a lot
of things in marketing there's a lot of
different disciplines that's PR that's
advertising that's events it's
everything that's going to position and
communicate your game uh out to the
world and this is where you need to
start asking questions you're going to
see this theme throughout my discussion
you need to start asking questions about
everything that this publisher that
you're talking to might do so the pr uh
the pr teams for example understand is
it them doing the pr is it a team of
people doing the pr are they Contracting
this out all of these things are valid
but finding out where are their PR teams
when they say they're going to do PR is
it just North America that's that's not
good there's a lot of people outside of
North America that buy video games and
they want to be talked to in their own
kind of with their own cultural nuances
and localize you know the information
you're giving them into their language
um do they include streamers and
YouTubers when they're talking about PR
uh if they don't include YouTubers and
streamers walk out of the door lock that
door and set the building on fire cuz
they don't know what they're doing uh
advertising how are they going to spend
this money like I think a lot of times
we talk to folks and we'll mention
advertising they don't even ask what
that means right I think that's and we
then give the information or at least
someone should give the information to
them but you need to ask how this money
will be spent okay they don't look at
the lineup and go great we got a great
advertising budget you need to find out
what that means and how they're going to
spend it and then what events do they go
to do they go to events do they have
people that go to events outside of
North America I think that's important
too there's a lot of amazing things like
bitsummit in Japan Ojo went to and
there's a lot of amazing events to go to
that are going to spread your game
outward so just be mindful of where
their PR activities are really happening
um and then of course a cohesive
campaign right you need to look at what
they've done what is their strategy what
have they done in the past how do they
customize that for different games
there's not a template to marketing
there's not a template to game
development I guess there is if you're
making some really clones you know clone
mobile games or something like that I
didn't look at you for a reason not you
not you um but you need to find out what
their strategy is find out what their
beliefs are in marketing the other part
is distribution you know let's I'm going
to be honest like 5 years ago Publishers
that we know or people I know or any
publisher could tell you well I can get
your game on Steam and that was a lot of
times enough for people to get excited
and sign up with them and I don't think
that's right and that's definitely not
right anymore I mean anyone can get your
game on Steam or you can bypass steam or
or you know you go on Playstation
there's itch there's all sorts of
amazing places to get your game directly
to
Consumers um but I will note when I was
thinking about this it's fa you know
fair or unfair Publishers do have their
advantage so you should ask them about
what these advantages might be cuz one
of the things I talk about um is
Publishers get direct lines sometimes to
a lot of people at them because they
have a lot of content then people that
you know steam or valve or Playstation
or Xbox or whoever um you have a direct
contact there and there's advantages of
having that for placement store
placement things like that and there's
things like publisher sales like again
right or wrong there's publisher sale
that devolver digital will get and it
will increase revenue for these games so
you need to ask your publisher what they
do and how they're going to make more
money than you would make on yours alone
when it comes to sales and
distribution um and the last thing I'd
say on this distribution is look what
else you're going to be amongst when you
know what the game what the the catalog
of games that publisher has um to see
where you sit there's some games uh
there's some Publishers out there or or
um you know Partners or whatever you
want to call them at this point in the
discussion um that specialize in things
there's Point click adventure folks that
do really really good have a lot of
point and click adventure and you would
sit amongst them and there's some
Synergy
there um so these are what a publisher
like I said should provide and I like in
this this is the basics when you're
buying a car and the car salesman says
well it's got four wheels it's got
windshield wipers and it'll take you
from point A to point B like yeah I know
that like sell me on what's next I think
this is the crucial moment for a lot of
developers that don't keep asking
questions or the publisher doesn't
provide more more answers of what
they're going to do Beyond those things
I I I don't know how to emphasize this
enough but these things that you see up
here that's the base level thing you
should be
expecting so what do I mean so what's
next what's after that
right and this is where I kind of got in
my head this discussion that was going
on discussion with developers we work
with and discussion with the the folks
that I work with at my company you know
what's next step and then we think it we
think it's a being a true partner and
what I what do I mean like that um well
let me actually let me back up those are
all the questions you're going to ask
that publisher ask them about funding
ask them about things but these when
you're finding a partner you're going to
ask them you know some questions I'm
going to get into but you also it's very
important to start asking questions to
the developers they worked with
previously right that's where you're
going to find a new angle a new um a new
way of of of maybe assessing this
publisher because they're going to tell
you what happened whether it was good or
bad um find of and here's another thing
when you're talking to developers from
this publish shirt that you're speaking
with um find don't just talk to the
people that sold a lot of copies cuz
they're probably going to be pretty
happy right and um they're probably
going to be pretty pleased with it go
find the uh developer that maybe you
know the game was fine but it didn't
sell a ton of copies because you maybe
can find a new dimension to that
discussion and uh you know find more
about how that develop excuse me how
that publisher carries themselves when
maybe things aren't as Sellar as you
know you had hoped so what can a partner
provide uh a true partner and again this
is I think a developer needs to start
looking and start assessing more um and
not stop at what does a publisher
provide um these things like I said
aren't easy to ascertain and um the
publisher is going to you know there's a
Salesman you're basically talking to
they want to sell you on them as a
company and um I'm going to speak to
creat creativity enthusiasm AKA giving a
[__] about your game and that's I mean
it's I know it's you know language but
like that's important part because you
don't want to sign up for somebody that
really doesn't care about your game once
it's signed on
um the stage and a spotlight a personal
relationship and brutal
honesty so when I say cre creativity I
don't just mean good ideas for launch
trailers I don't just mean like hey what
about some slow-mo action and some
slow-mo music it's going to be beautiful
like I'm not talking about those kind of
things I'm talking about they're
creative enthusiastic about every
element of your game that's just
marketing that's distribution that's
production that's uh funding working
with you you and the way you may have
money already and doing things smart and
different uh to make sure that you're
happy and that you're comfortable so
don't just check stuff off a list these
are people that are thinking and being
creative about every part of your game
um again look at the Publishers body of
work that's the easiest thing to do you
can scroll through their YouTube channel
you can scroll through their website you
can scroll through Metacritic you can
see what they've worked on you can see
where they've been successful and where
they maybe of Applied creativity to
everything they do um you need to find
out if they've done what you've you know
done things that are successful before
and how that might apply to your
game I mean frankly they're going to
show you all the best things they've
ever done and the big fancy launch
trailers um or they could I'm just
saying a good one's going to show you
some smart thinking and I'm not going to
try and pimp us out as a publisher
that's the whole point I just want to
talk about in general but one thing I
would do want to reference because I use
this in my discussion with developers um
as a point of when you're thinking about
every aspect of it and this is a game
called Hotline Miami that we worked on
um in 2011
2012 um and this is the point I want to
make is this ridiculous phone number we
set up for Hotline Miami it was just
late one night and we're thinking of fun
things to do and if You' played the game
part of the game is you get these crazy
calls um from a telephone he gets these
crazy messages so we thought it would be
fun to um we found a Google Voice number
in hotline or excuse me in Miami Florida
and uh we grabbed it and we left a weird
message and we start leaving this phone
number in uh uh you know press releases
website social media so we just we sent
that out for a week never checked it
that that'd be funny what if people
start calling it what if they leave
messages to open it up it's got 4,000
voicemails and like 600 text messages
which I didn't know you could do on
Google Voice and was very concerning
what people were writing um but the cool
thing my point with this is is it's not
don't just look at the high level fancy
things that's going to you think are I
mean those are very important trailers
are important booths are important but
look for where people are thinking of
things like this that cost nothing and
really like this engage the community
and get them excited and talking about
it um because that's where I think
you're going to find that difference in
creativity um the next thing is stage
and Spotlight a good publisher should
put this developer first right this is
important for your your personal
fulfillment as a developer but it's also
very important for you as a studio and
you as maybe a loan developer that when
you're done with this game people know
about your work and that you did it and
you were the one that made this and that
when you're ready to to your next thing
that they know who you are um it's it's
it's not about necessarily whose logo is
bigger but just make sure like that you
are always Center Stage whenever your
gaming is being presented and not the
develop excuse me not the publisher
putting their name out there
first and a good partner will will do
this and I will be you know Frank with
you like we fight for this have to fight
you know platforms and first- party
people to say I know what your rules are
but you got to take devolver digital off
this you need to put the developer on on
there because I think it's very
important that people understand that
they made it I can't make games I can
barely put together a PowerPoint I
promise you that and and I think it's
important for you and your studio to
have that kind of Spotlight put on
you um the one thing I will note and I
think you know ojiro is up here it's a
really good example not all developers
necessarily want that Spotlight when we
were first working together we were had
to go to a twitch stage was it paxi we
had some twitch
thing and you know he came to me he was
like you know I'm not necessar I'm not
super excited about being in the
spotlight on this one and so um you're
publisher your partner needs to
understand that need understand what
your little ID idiosyncrasies might be
what you are comfortable doing and maybe
you the publisher the excuse me not you
the developer you the the publisher
might need to speak for your game okay
and and not talking about marketing
bullet points from a fact sheet I'm
talking about knowing your game inside
and out being able to demo the hell out
of that game in front of somebody speak
for you and represent you in your studio
well um I think this is a pretty crucial
crucial part because the whole idea is
you guys can focus on your game you're
not going to be able to go to every show
you're not going to be able to go to
every event and you need to make sure
that Partners out there that you trust
will represent your game well and speak
kind of in the tone that you want it to
be uh
presented okay this one is me almost
tearing or tearing up over there when
ojiro was up here because
um it's a personal relationship like you
need to make sure it's this is a very
aspirational thing but you're looking
for personal relationship with this
folks um this this person this partner
you're going to work with um they're
going to be a part of your lives for 18
months 2 years 5 years whatever it is
and you need to make sure that you can
develop some you don't have to
necessarily like them but you have some
sort of personal working good
relationship with them you don't might
I'm sorry you may not want to have a
beer with them and spend the night at
their house and staying up all night
playing NBA Jam um but you do have to
have have some sort of personal
relationship with them and you need to
understand the organization of the
company itself right the guy that me
let's say me that is signing your game
or let's not say me I'm not supposed to
use examples of me um the person that's
signing your game uh you need to make
sure if that's not the person you're
dealing with on a day-to-day basis who
is that understand how that company
Works how that publisher works and who
are the people you can go to and speak
with when uh things need to get done and
you're not talking you know to the the
person's just your Handler the person
that can actually execute and make
things happen for
you oh the other part I think I have it
up here yeah can they work uh can they
contact them at night weekends or mid
qutis I know it's kind of a joke but
like you need to understand that I we
you know you guys don't work 9 to5 in
fact I'm pretty sure it's more like 5 to
n based on the people I work with like
it's you guys have insane hours right so
you're going to need someone there
someone you can be able to talk to and
contact uh at any point and I think you
need to talk to the other developers
they work with to see how that goes
because if it's say 9 to-5 company and
you know you're going to get an
answering machine or you're going to get
you're not going to be able to get a
hold of them that's something important
you're going to need to know because
things go wrong constantly as you know
and then what are the lengths that
people are you know this this this
publisher this potential partner is
willing to go for you um you a lot of
the people I know I'm talking to and a
lot of people you work with they're very
small companies and they're the same
people that are making the game or the
same people plugging in the computers to
the events and so you need to understand
how far this partner this publisher will
go and they're not uh they're not too
fancy to you know go get your breakfast
tacos when you need them when you're
setting up your setting up your demo
kiosk and then the last thing is brutal
honesty if you have those other things
um a personal relationship for example
uh the brutal brutal honesty won't be a
problem and I mean this this is going to
be a two-way street when I talk about
brutal honesty um there's there's got a
lot of uncomfortable talks that might
happen when you're working with uh you
know a business like a publisher right
uh money is an uncomfortable subject uh
not just the initial talks about money
but ongoing talks about needing more
money and then when money starts rolling
in from uh the game being sold you know
understanding and being very clear how
that money is coming in and where it's
going being able to talk about these
things is plainly and openly is very
important and then talking about about I
put on here tell each other that you
suck you need to be able to um the the
publisher the partner that you're
talking to needs to be able to tell you
what they think honestly about the game
and you need to be able to accept that
criticism and either take it or dismiss
it I know we talked about quite a bit
it's little I was watching your your
your your talk and there's a lot of
elements that were like eh I personally
didn't like that no jir was like cool
[__] you I'm keeping it in there and
it's great and that's the kind of things
you need to be able to say to a real
partner right this same time um he needs
to be able to tell me um I'm sorry I'm
picking on you there were supposed to be
other developers up here that are now
sitting in the back I
see um the the the other thing that I
would say here is that um you need to be
able to uh tell the that partner that
publisher that you uh don't like what
they're doing you need to speak up if
you don't like how the game's being
presented you don't like the trailer you
don't like whatever it is the steam page
whatever it is speak up it's your game
take a hold of it and tell them that
doing a bad job on
something um and the last thing I want
to say on this this brutal honesty thing
is um this comes up in a lot of
discussions when I'm talking with
developers and they tell me they're
talking to another publisher if a
publisher guarantees you success they're
[__] lying to you okay there's no
guarantee of success um I talk I got the
clearance to talk about this but this
guy Paul Hart who made the game called
Fistful of gun um it was a great game it
didn't sell really well and we talked
about it we were honest with each other
the whole time what these uh what these
projections are looking like and then
once the game wasn't doing well what
could we do to hopefully you know the
game recouped made money but how we can
maximize it cuz he spent a lot of time
on this game and we maybe didn't do a
good job and he maybe didn't make the
best game he possibly could no one needs
to point fingers here you need to be
brutally honest like how do we [__]
make this work now that the game isn't
going you know as well as we' hoped so I
think that you need to talk like I said
to other developers and see how they
handle not only success but not success
I'm not going to say failures but not
success um there are a lot more things
in this there really I just have some
things I thought were important to bring
up um but this extends like this you
need to find this deeper level of
commitment that extends past this kind
of publisher developer relationship it's
this is not an all-encompassing list um
but my point is I think you just need to
look past the basics and what the
publisher should give you and look beond
on like what you really need as a person
because you all have different
situations you all have different
circumstances which you're running
operating so you need to look past that
and ask as many questions as possible so
this leads to this last little piece
about some common issues that crop up
right um this is all again anecdotal but
I thought they were worthy of um these
amazing slides that I put together um
clearly some of these are related to the
publisher partner kind of elements that
I just talked about um so I'll make it
kind of quick intellectual property IP
um if the game is is your baby the IP is
its Soul okay so you need to take care
of both and hold on to both do not sell
your IP do not make it part of the
agreement um there's a lot of reasons
why um obviously you know sequels and
things like that but just that's ends up
being one of the most important parts of
this and it strangely still comes up in
conversations we have like do you guys
want IP and if they want IP that's
that's a whole another level um you
should absolutely hold on to it but
owning it is just kind of a part of it
and need to be mindful how your IP is
being presented right um and how it's
being positioned overall um if there's
damage done to it while you are
promoting the game marketing game it
doesn't just affect that game it affects
your studio and it affects any future
games in that series and the last part
is from the best movie All Time movie of
all time space balls and the idea is
your IP is not just your game remember
that it is about any sort of
opportunities that exist within it so
whether it's t-shirts
uh comic books that are made Movies
featured length film downwell the movie
which is coming to theaters next
year um is it apparently okay
good I got the IP so um but it's
something important to keep in mind that
it's not just the game itself and that
you know these things do not let a
partner whoever it is mess with how your
game's presented and how your IP is
presented um do not this is like I want
to have a whole another quiet talk in a
room with each and every one of you
about agreements do not settle do not
assume anything in agreement okay ask
the questions it's your right to do it
um one example please please please be
very clear on how the money flows into
the game and back out of the project
when it's done there's there's a whole
another talk that would be way more
boring than this one but it's really
important of understanding how your game
is going to be recouped how the cost the
publisher might put out there might
recoup them how they're going to recoup
when they're going to be recouped
because it could be the difference
between um how much money you're making
like not only short-term but long-term
as well uh it can be very tricky so ask
for examples uh one thing that we do is
we provide a spreadsheet where you can
literally see like where the money is
going in and then you type in the unit
sold and the average unit price and it
tells you shows you exactly how it it
comes back out I think this is so
important because you do not want to be
wrong on something like that especially
after the fact um and then I put lock
your [__] up to developers like make
sure you have clear agreements uh
amongst yourselves and the Freelancers
you work with um we can't help you if
you had an agreement a handshake we
chest bump or whatever it is that about
the music or about some freelance work
you know that if you don't have an
agreement there's nothing we can do
about it as a publisher like that's the
agreement you made and often times
people start asking you know well what
do I do I need to can you guys pay them
this money and that's not an our
agreement it becomes a really tough
conversation have so make sure that you
understand you know have very clear
understanding ideally and agreement with
other people you work with and the last
piece is poor communication do not save
changes to the very end when you're
working with a partner like um or a
publisher or partner you need to uh if
the game's going to be late bring it up
as soon as you think it's going to be
late because that helps everyone
including yourself involved having you
know making knowing who the decision
makers are talking to them and being
very informed back and forth of what's
going on is super important I know it's
pretty generic to say like have good
communication but it can't emphasize it
enough um you are in charge of your game
make sure you're in charge of your game
stay in charge of your game and the last
part is related to what we talked about
before sustainability I think that's a
huge thing that people don't think about
um at least we you know we see it with
developers we work with and developers
we don't is uh understanding
sustainability of your publisher and
your sustainability uh if you sign on
with somebody like I said there's lots
of them out there that call themselves
Publishers uh you need to do your
research like we're talking about that
they're going to be around when your
game launches because if you sign a deal
and they go away that's really really
going to hurt you and your situation so
kind of know who funds them right who's
funding that develop excuse me who's
funding that publisher how do they have
money and um what are they going to do
are they going to be around right but
also don't plan for yourself plan on
your funding when you're pitching do not
lowball a publisher that helps nobody
you need to understand what's going to
take to launch your game and then what's
going to take for those two or three
months after your game is launched when
people start when the money starts
coming in you know steam PlayStation
they all pay not it's not like someone
buys the game and they hand you your
money right it takes months sometimes
you 6 weeks to two months for your money
to come through so if you've only funded
your game up to release you might have
two you know two months that you don't
have any money coming in and we see this
time and time again and you know it's
fine we can keep advancing people but I
think it's good because if you're in an
agreement and the one runs out and you
really need money and you ask them for
more they could ask for you know royalty
change and things like that things you
don't want to get get into and then also
have an idea what your next project is
if possible it's always good to like if
something doesn't go well you're not
spinning your wheels for a few months
wondering what am I going to do next I
know that's easier said than done from
the publisher up here um what do I have
up here oh provocative
recap um so there's lots of publishing
options that a lot of people that do a
lot of things it's very important to
understand why what that publish you're
working with what they do what Their
angle is you know what they do well what
they might not do as well um understand
your partner complete and you know
everything you can about that partner
and the last part or second last part is
you're in charge so stay in charge never
forget that never forget you're the one
that made this game um ultimately they
need you more than you need them you
could self-publish if you want to and
that's my last point self-publish I mean
every there's a lot of people that do it
very successfully um and it's much
better than getting into a bad B deal I
know there might be tough situations you
might be in but you know you don't you
don't need a [__] publisher so you
can self-publish if you need to it's
better than being in a bad
agreement and now if you have any
questions I'm I'm happy to answer oh no
questions apparently no
[Applause]
questions but thank you very much for
coming out